<!-- chapter utilities -->
<chapter id="chap.eventlog">
    <title>The Event log program</title>
    <para>
        Most experiments will record event data.  Event data files are
        record the data taken from the experiment event by event.
        The format of event data files is identical to the format of data in
        ring buffers.
        See the chapter:
        <link linkend="chapter.ringformat">Format of EventData In Ring Buffers</link>
        for a description of what to expect in an event file.   The
        <filename>$DAQROOT/include/DataFormat.h</filename> header is
        also helpful as it provides C/C++ structure definitions for
        data in ring buffers and event files.
    </para>
    <para>
        The event logger takes data from any ring (local or remote via the
        networked proxy ring subsystem).  When a begin run item is seen,
        a new event file is started.  Event files are broken into segments.
        This is done to ensure that files do not exceed maximum sizes set
        by some filesystems and NFS.  By default, the segment size is a bit
        less than 2Gbytes. When replaying data it is important to keep this in 
        mind, and replay all segments of a run.
    </para>
    <para>
        The Event logger places output files in a specified directory.
        By default, this directory is the working directory at the time the
        application was started.  The default ring from which the program
        accepts data is <literal>tcp://localhost/</literal><replaceable>username</replaceable>
        where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is the name of the user running
        the program.
    </para>
    <para>
        The event log program includes a <option>--oneshot</option> option that
        records a single run and then exits.  The <option>--oneshot</option>
        option also creates synchronization files in the event file directory that
        allow a controlling program to know when the event logger is
        running and when it is about to exit.
    </para>
    <para>
        The control files are:
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>.started</filename></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Created when the program is ready to record data.
                        The controlling program can then start a run.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><filename>.exited</filename></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Created when the program has closed the event file and
                        is about to exit.  The controlling program can move
                        any event files to a final directory if desired.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </para>
    <example>
        <title>Taking data from a remote ring</title>
        <programlisting>
eventlog --source=tcp://spdaq22/fox --path=/user/0400x/stagearea/current --oneshot
        </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
        The full reference documentation for the program is in the
        <link linkend="manpage.eventlog">event log reference page</link>.
    </para>
</chapter>
    
<!-- /chapter -->

<!-- manpage 1daq -->

<refentry id="manpage.eventlog">
  <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>eventlog</refentrytitle>
     <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
     <refname>eventlog</refname>
     <refpurpose>Record Event Data to Disk.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
	<command>
eventlog <optional>options...</optional>
	</command>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1>
     <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
     <para>
	Records event data verbatim from ring buffers to disk files.
        The program monitors the source ring buffer for a begin run item.
        At that point it opens an event file for that run and begins to record
        data from the ring.  
     </para>
     <para>
        Runs are recorded in files in the target directory.
        Event files are named
        <filename>run-runnumber-segment.evt</filename> where
        <literal>runnumber</literal> is the run number of the run
        taken from the begin run item, <literal>segment</literal> is a file
        segment numbered from zero.
     </para>
     <para>
        Runs are segmented in file that are no larger than a segment size.
        This is done to avoid creating files that are too large for a file system
        to handle or too large for NFS to accurately serve.
     </para>
     <para>
        An option allows the program to be started by a controlling program
        for a single run (e.g. by the readout GUI).
     </para>
     <para>
        Options have sensible defaults.  See OPTIONS below.
     </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
     <title>
	OPTIONS
     </title>
     <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--source</option>=<replaceable>ringuri</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
		<para>
                    Defines the event source as a Ring buffer Uniform Resource
                    Identifier (URI).  The URI can be for a local or a remote
                    ring buffer.  By default the ring:
                    <literal>tcp://localhost/</literal><replaceable>username</replaceable>
                    where <replaceable>username</replaceable> is the username
                    of the account running the program.
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--path</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Provides the path to the directory in which the program will
                    write its event files. By default, this is
                    current working directory at the time <application>eventlog</application>
                    is started.
                </para>
                <para>
                    <application>eventlog</application> ensures that the path is
                    a directory and is writable.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--segmentsize</option>=<replaceable>size-spec</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Specifies the size of the files segments created.
                    <parameter>size-spec</parameter> can be any of an integer number
                    of bytes or an integer followed by one of the suffixes:
                    <literal>g</literal>, <literal>m</literal>, <literal>k</literal>
                    that multiply the integer by a gigabyte, a megabyte and a kilobyte
                    repsectively.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The default value is a <literal>1900m</literal>, which should
                    be suitable for most operating environments.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--oneshot</option></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    When present, the program only records a single run, then
                    exits.  The program will also create the
                    <filename>.started</filename> file in the target directory
                    when it's ready to record data, and the
                    <filename>.exited</filename> file when it's about to exit.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
  </refsect1>


</refentry>


<!-- /manpage -->