<!-- chapter utilities -->

<chapter id="chapter.dvdburner">
    <title>DvdBurner - Using Tcl to burn runs to DVD</title>
    <para>
        <application>DvdBurner</application> is a Tcl package that allows you to
        burn NSCL data runs to DVD.  The DvdBurner package breaks the data up
        among as many DVD's as needed, however it requires that the data
        from a single run fit completely on a single DVD.
        The package is completey described in the
        <link linkend="manpage.dvdburner">dvdburner package manpage</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
        To use
        <application>DvdBurner</application>
        you must make the package known to your script.  Doing this involves
        both making the location of the package known to the Tcl package loader
        and requiring the package.
        The following example shows how to do it assuming that you've defined
        the envirionment varible DAQROOT to point to the directory in which the
        NSCL DAQ system is installed.  At the NSCL, this directory is usually
        <filename>/usr/opt/daq/someversion</filename> where
        <literal>someversion</literal> is the version of nscldaq you are using.
    </para>
    <example>
        <title>Requesting the DvdBurner package</title>
        <programlisting>
set libdir [file join $::env(DAQROOT) TclLibs]
set auto_path [concat $libdir $auto_path]

package require DvdBurner
        </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
        The example prepends the path to the NSCL DAQ libraries to the
        <varname>auto_path</varname>
        that lists the directories searched by the Tcl package loader.
        Prepending ensures that if there are accidental duplicate package names,
        we get the one in the NSCL DAQ software.
    </para>
    <para>
        Typically, the only thing you'll want your script to do is burn a set
        of runs to DVD, partitioning the data amongst several DVDs as needed.
        The script below shows how to do write runs 100 through 150 to DVD:
    </para>
    <example>
        <title>Writing runs to DVD using <application>DvdBurner</application></title>
        <programlisting>
DvdBurner::CreateDvds [list 100 150]
        </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
        If the second parameter to
        <function>DvdBurner::CreateDvds</function>
        is omitted, all runs starting with  first parameter are written to DVD.
        With no parameters, all runs are written to DVD:
    </para>
    <example>
        <title>Writing all runs to DVD</title>
        <programlisting>
DvdBurner::CreateDvds
        </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
        Writes all runs to DVD.
    </para>
</chapter>


<!-- /chapter -->

<!-- manpage 3tcl -->

<refentry id="manpage.dvdburner">
  <refmeta>
     <refentrytitle>DvdBurner</refentrytitle>
     <manvolnum>1tcl</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
     <refname>DvdBurner package</refname>
     <refpurpose>Burn NSCL Data to DVD</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
	<command>
package require DvdBurner
	</command>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <cmdsynopsis>
    <command>
DvdBurner::CreateDvds ?range?
    </command>
</cmdsynopsis>
<cmdsynopsis>
    <command>
DvdBurner::BurnDVD iso
    </command>
</cmdsynopsis>

  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1>
     <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
     <para>
	The
        <application>DvdBurner</application> package provides the capability to
        burn an arbitary ISO image or set of NSCL data acquisition systsem
        event data and associated data to DVD. 
     </para>
    <cmdsynopsis>
    <command>
DvdBurner::CreateDvds ?range?
    </command>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <para>
        creates DVDs from a set of recorded data taking runs.  The data and
        run meta-data are recorded to DVD.  If necessary, several DVDs are
        created.  Data are split so that all of the data associated with a run
        is on a single DVD (not split across more than one DVD.
        See, however "Dependencies and Restrictions" below.
    </para>
<cmdsynopsis>
    <command>
DvdBurner::BurnDVD isofile
    </command>
</cmdsynopsis>
    <para>
        Burns the pre-built ISO image in the file <parameter>isofile</parameter>
        to DVD.
     </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
     <title>Dependencies and Restrictions</title>
     <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            <application>growisofs</application> must be isntalled and in
                the user's path.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The DVD must either be named <filename>/dev/cdrom</filename> or
            the environment variable <literal>DVDROM</literal> must be
            defined to be the name of the DVD burner to use.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The variable DvdBurner::DVD holds the path to the DVD burner
            device and can be modified at run time any time after the package
            has been <command>require</command>ed.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The DVD device must be writable by <application>growisofs</application>.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The variable DvdBurner::DVDSize holds the number of megabytes
            a DVD can hold  It can be modified from its default value of
            <literal>4000</literal> if necessary.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The <function>DvdBurner::CreateDvds</function> command will fail
            if there are runs that won't fit on single DVDS.  Errors in the
            NSCL file structure can also cause failures.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The variable <varname>DvdBurner::ISOFSroot</varname> holds the
            directory in which the run data will be marshalled and the
            ISO images built.  The initial value is
            <filename>/scratch/$tcl_platform(user)/isos</filename>
            where <varname>tcl_platform(user)</varname> is your username.
         </para></listitem>    
     </itemizedlist>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>


<!-- /manpage -->