<!-- chapter utilities -->
<chapter>
    <title>glom</title>
    <para>
        The NSCL event builder is a pipeline.  At the front of the
        pipeline is the fragment orderer. The fragment orderer
        accepts fragments from an arbitrary number of sources, orders them by
        timestamp and emits them in timestamp order.
        If you want events actually built from these sorted fragments, your
        event building pipeline will need an element to glue together fragments
        whose timestamps are within a specified coincidence window, and
        create ring items from them.
    </para>
    <para>
        The program that does this is <application>glom</application>.
        <footnote><para>The online urban dictionary at http://www.urbandictionary.com
        gives as part of definition 3: "to collect or cluster together. "</para></footnote>
    </para>
    <para>
        Glom accepts fragments on standard input and emits ring items on
        standard output. These may be further processed in later stages of a pipeline
        or they can be piped into <application>stdintoring</application> to
        insert them in a ring buffer for further distribution.
    </para>
    <para>
        For reference information on glom see:
        <link linkend='daq1_glom' endterm='daq1_glom_title' />
    </para>
</chapter>
<!-- /chapter -->

<!-- manpage 1daq -->
      <refentry id="daq1_glom">
        <refmeta>
           <refentrytitle id='daq1_glom_title'>glom</refentrytitle>
           <manvolnum>1daq</manvolnum>
        </refmeta>
        <refnamediv>
           <refname>glom</refname>
           <refpurpose>Glue event fragments together into events</refpurpose>
        </refnamediv>
        
        <refsynopsisdiv>
          <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>
glom <replaceable>options</replaceable>
          </command>
          </cmdsynopsis>

        </refsynopsisdiv>
        <refsect1>
           <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
           <para>
            Glom is a filter that accepts event ordered event fragments on stdin
            and emits event ring items on standard output.  Event fragments that
            represent non physics triggers are just passed through, with the
            event fragment header stripped off so that they become their initial
            ring items again.
           </para>
           <para>
            Any errors glom wants to complain about are emitted to its standard
            error.  It is therefore normally a bad idea to have glom's standard
            output and standard error pointed to the same sink.
            Glom's behavior is controlled by command line options that are
            documented in <literal>OPTIONS</literal> below.
           </para>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
           <title>
              OPTIONS
           </title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--nobuild</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            If this option is present, glom won't attempt to glue
                            together event fragments, but will emit each event fragment
                            as a single vent.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>--dt</option> <replaceable>ticks</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This mandatory parameter provides the number of
                            timestamp ticks that define a coincidence interval
                            when building events.  The value of <replaceable>ticks</replaceable>
                            is ignored but currently necessary when <option>--nobuild</option>
                            is speicified.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>KNOWN ISSUES</title>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    <option>--dt</option> should probably not be necessary if
                    <option>--nobuild</option> is present.
                    </para></listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </refsect1>
                                
                
      </refentry>

<!-- /manpage -->