

<!-- chapter utilities -->

<chapter id="chapter.chanlog">
   <title>Epics Channel logging</title>
   <para>
      <application>chanlog</application>
      is a utility that allows you to log the values of a set of EPICS
      channels.
      <link linkend="manpage.chanlog">The chanlog manpage</link>
      provides full reference material for chanlog program.
   </para>
   <para>
      Chanlog allows you to:
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem><para>
	    Interactively view a set of channel values.
	 </para></listitem>
	 <listitem><para>
	    Write or append a set of channel values to a text file.
	 </para></listitem>
	 <listitem><para>
	    Pipe a set of channel values to a program for processing.
	  </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </para>
</chapter>
<!-- /chapter -->
    
<!-- manpage 1epics -->

    <refentry id="manpage.chanlog">
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>chanlog</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1epics</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>chanlog</refname>
        <refpurpose>Write a set of channels to file</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
chanlog <replaceable>channelfile</replaceable> <replaceable>outfile</replaceable>
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
       Logs  the  names, values and units of a set of EPICS channels to file.  In the
       command invocation,
       <replaceable>channelfile</replaceable>
       is a file that contains the names of the channels
       to  lookup and log.  If
       <replaceable>channelfile</replaceable> is
        <literal>-</literal>, then the channels are taken from stdin.
       <replaceable>outfile</replaceable>
       is the name of a file to which the channels will be logged.  If
       <replaceable>outfile</replaceable>
       is <literal>-</literal>, the output is sent to stdout.
        </para>
        <para>
       The  channel  file  is  an ordinary text file that contains the names of EPICS
       channels, each channel is separated by whitespace (note that a newline  counts
       as  whitespace).   No  comments  are allowed, in contrast to the form of input
       file expected by e.g. epicsdisplay.  The following is a sample input file:
        </para>
        <programlisting>
       Z001DV Z002DH
       Z003DV
       Z004QA

       Z012QB
        </programlisting>
        <para>
       This file will output the values and units for  5  channels:
       <literal>Z001DV,  Z002DH,
       Z003DV, Z004QA</literal> and <literal>Z004QA</literal>.
        </para>
	<para>
	   Output will consist of a line of text for each channel in the input
           file.  Each line will consist of a set of white-space separated 
	   components.  The first component is the name of  a channel followed
           by a colon.  The second element is the channel value.
	   The final element is the channel engineering units.
	</para>
	<para>
	   If the value of a channel cannot be gotten, the remainder of the
	   line following the channel name will be the error message
	   generated for that channel for example:
	   <literal>Z001DH: ca_pend_io failed User specified timeout on IO
        operation expired</literal>.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
       <title>EXAMPLES</title>
       <para>
          All of the examples assume that a file named 
	  <filename>channels.txt</filename> has been created
	  that contains the set of channel names of interest, and that 
	  <application>chanlog</application> is in your path.
       </para>
       <example>
          <title>Viewing a set of channel values interactively</title>
	  <programlisting>
chanlog channels.txt -
	  </programlisting>
       </example>
       <example>
          <title>Writing a set of channels to a file</title>
	  <programlisting>
chanlog channels.txt somefile.out
          </programlisting>
        </example>
	<example>
	   <title>Appending a set of channels to a file</title>
	   <programlisting>
chanlog channels.txt - >>somefile.out
           </programlisting>
        </example>
	<example>
	   <title>Piping a set of channels to a program for processing</title>
	   <programlisting>
chanlog channels.txt - | someprogram
           </programlisting>
         </example>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
       <title>DEPENDENCIES</title>
       <para>
          <itemizedlist>
	     <listitem><para>
	        Epics software must be installed and located by the installer
             </para></listitem>
             <listitem><para>
	        The Epics utility <application>caRepeater</application> should
                be in your path.  This is in the architecture specific 
		<filename>bin</filename> directory of the Epics installation.
              </para></listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
       </para>
    </refsect1>
    </refentry>

<!-- /manpage -->