<!-- chapter utilities -->

<chapter id="chapter.epicsdisplay">
    <title>The epics display utility</title>
    <para>
        The
        <application>epicsdisplay</application>
        utility provides a tabular display of an arbitrary set of epics channels.
        It is possible to configure a set of channels to be displayed on a chart
        recorder at the bottom of the display as well.
        Complete reference documentation is available at the
        <link linkend="manpage.epicsdisplay">epicsdisplay reference page</link>
    </para>
    <para>
        <application>epicsdisplay</application> reads in a configuration file.
        The configuration file is compatible with
        <link linkend="manpage.controlpush">the controlpush</link> application,
        which uses it to fetch epics channesl and make them known to
        <application>epicsdisplay</application>.
        <application>epicsdisplay</application> interprets additional information
        in the file as metadata that describes such things as:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>
                Alarms on the channel and how to display the alarm condition.
                      </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>
                Whether or not a channel should be displayed as a trace on a
                chart recorder graph at the bottom of the window.
                      </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        Extensive online help is provided via the
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Help</guimenu><guimenuitem>Topics...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
        menu entry.
    </para>
</chapter>

<!-- /chapter  -->

<!-- manpage 1tcl -->

    <refentry id="manpage.epicsdisplay">
    <beginpage />
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>epicsdisplay
        <productname>NSCLRingDAQ</productname>
        <productnumber>10.0+</productnumber>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Ron</firstname>
                <surname>Fox</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        </refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1tcl</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo />
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>epicsdisplay</refname>
        <refpurpose>Display epics channels</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>
epicsdisplay channel file
            </command>
        </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
       Monitors  a  set  of EPICS channels in tabular and, optionally, chart recorder
       form.  channelfile is the name of a file that describes the epics channels  to
       monitor.   The  file consists of two types of text lines; comments and channel
       lines.  Comment lines begin with the hash character lines begin with a channel
       name  followed  by  whitespace,  followed  by  an  optional  comment.   If the
       optional comment contains the special word ââchartââ, the channel is added  to
       the chart recorder.
        </para>
        <para>
       Channels can also have alarms defined on them.  An alarm is said to fire whenâ[m
       ever the channel value is outside of a  ânominalâ  window.   Alarms  are  also
       defined  using special keywords in the comment field of the channel.  The keyâ[m
       word nominal indicates that the next word on the line  defines  the  channelâs
       nominal window.  The nominal window definition can be defined either symmetriâ[m
       cally or asymmetrically about a nominal value.  The nominal window can also be
       defined  in  absolute  terms  or  in  terms  of a percentage of nominal value.
       Describing nominal windows is most easily done via example.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>nominal 35:3</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Defines a symmetric nominal window about the nominal  value  35.   This
                        nominal window is the range 32 through 38.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>nominal 35:10%</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Defines  a  nominal interval that is +/- 10% of 35... e.g. the interval
                          32.5 through 38.5
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>nominal 35+3-4</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                      Defines a nominal window between 31 and 38.  Similarly:
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>nominal 35+5%-10%</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Defines the nominal interval 32.5 through 36.75.
                        Note that  for  asymmetric
                        intervals  mixes  of  absolute  and  percentage  tolerances are
                        allowed.  Furthermore, the - and + are interchangeable.
                    </para>
                 </listitem>
             </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>
       When a channel transitions to the alarmed state, actions defined on  the
       comment
       line for the channel are taken.  Actions are defined by the keyword
       alarmmactions followed by a comma separated list  of  actions.   Supported  actions
       are:
       </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>page</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The alarm is added to a page that describes all the current alarms.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>beep</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A  beep  is  periodically  emitted  while the channel is in the alarmed
                          state.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>popup</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A popup window is displayed when the alarm is in the alarmed state.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><literal>color=colorspec</literal></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
              The alarm is displayed with the specified colorspec colored background.
              colorspec  is  a color using any color specification that is recognized
              by Tcl.  (.e.g. color=red  is the same as color=&#035;ff0000).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect1>
        <refsect1>
            <title>OPERATING INSTRUCTIONS</title>
            <para>
       The display is divided into three sections. The top section is the channel 
       table.  The middle section the chart recorder section and the bottom section the
       chart control panel.
        </para>
        <para>
       While it appears as if the table section has no controls,  in  reality  it  is
       possible  to  resize  all  of  the columns of the table.  Expanding the window
       width adds space to the right most, Comment column.  All other columns may  be
       expanded by dragging their borders with the mouse.
        </para>
        <para>
       The  chart  recorder control panel allows the user to perform a few operations
       on the chart.  The Clear button resets the time to 0 and clears the data accumulated so far.
        </para>
        <para>
       The  rightmost  three  controls  manage  the  time  scale of the chart widget.
       Changes to these widgets do nothing until the Set  button  is  clicked.    The
       widget  states at that time determine the scale of the chart recorder.  If the
       ââAuto Rangeââ checkbutton is set, the time scale will change  dynamically  to
       accomodate  the  full  time  range  of values.  If unchecked, the value in the
       entry widget labelled <literal>Range (min):</literal>  determines the width in  time  of  the
       chart.  The chart is scrolled as needed (by 10% of the range) to keep the most
       recent data visible.
       </para>
        
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Dependencies</title>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>
            Requires the
            <link linkend="manpage.controlpush">controlpush</link> utility.
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>
                Requires the server port manager application.
            </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
    </refsect1>
    </refentry>

    

<!-- /manpage -->